DAVID KRENTZLIN

Address Hinrich-Thieß-Str. 52d

22844 Norderstedt

Germany

E-Mail <u>david.krentzlin@gmail.com</u>

Phone +49 170 6890 588

Github https://github.com/certainty

Website http://www.lisp-unleashed.de/me



PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

I am a programming language geek, somewhat obsessed with typed functional programming, fascinated by high traffic distributed systems, a self driven learner and growing teacher.

With 20 years of experience as a software engineer I eat, sleep and breathe code, know how to approach complex systems and build components that meet today's demands.

I understand the importance of people and how to create an environment in which they can work together towards a common goal and find good solutions for challenging problems.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer

XING SE

Dec 2015 - Today

XING One - GraphQL Gateway

- Backend engineer on the core infrastructure team that planned, designed, developed and rolled out a GraphQL Gateway as the new data access platform for XING with currently ~20 million req/ day
- Improved data handling for mobile and web clients by providing a faster, safer and more robust way to fetch data via GraphQL
- Planned and drove the development of bigger parts fo the gateway like file uploads, caching and logged-out support
- Increased availability, resilience and performance of the GraphQL service through systematic measurement, profiling, monitoring and finally implementing the required changes
- Built fast, secure, resilient and reliable HTTP level service to service communication
- Created and carried out workshops to train our engineers in GraphQL, Scala and XING One
- <u>Leveraged knowledge</u> in Scala, Go lang, Ruby, GraphQL, Distributed Systems, Network programming

XING Webservices and public API

- Maintained and operated the RESTful API that is the primary data access mechanism for the XING mobile clients with more than 400 million reg/day
- <u>Leveraged knowledge</u> in Ruby, Ruby on Rails, AMQP, Caching, Redis, MySQL and Network

XING Messenger End-to-End Encryption

- Planned, designed and documented the integration of a Double-Ratchet Protocol for the XING Messenger together with external crypto experts
- Designed and developed the backend integration to bring End-To-End Encryption to the XING Messenger
- Worked closely together with mobile engineers, backend engineers and external experts to bring the required encryption knowledge into the team and enable the delivery of End-To-End Encryption.
- <u>Leveraged knowledge</u> in Ruby, AMQP, Cryptography, MySQL, Network protocols

XING Messenger

- Introduced highly available, resilient and performant real-time update channel for the XING messenger
- Designed and implemented new RESTful APIs to enable new features on the XING messenger
- Developed load testing component to verify and measure the real time update channel of the XING messenger
- Conducted performance and load testing for the new messenger platform
- Improved the quality of the code base by driving and supporting a software design shift that provided a better basis for the development of features
- Developed the infrastructure to integrate the real-time channel written in Elixir with the XING platform
- <u>Leveraged knowledge</u> in Ruby, Ruby on Rails, Elixir, Phoenix AMQP, Cryptography, MySQL and network programming

Senior Software Developer OMCnet Internet Service GmbH 2007 - Nov 2015

- Introduced more reliable and capable version of E-Mail policy service to enforce policies on the MTA
- Automated operations workflows and developed solutions to manage a fleet of dedicated and shared servers
- Designed, planned, set up and operated high-available solutions for storage and web services
- Developed web based management interfaces for the dedicated and shared hosting environment
- Introduced continuous integration pipeline to speed up the delivery features for the internal products
- Designed, setup and implement configuration as code with puppet
- <u>Leveraged knowledge</u> in Ruby, C/C++, Perl, Scheme, PostgresQL, MySQL, network protocols, operations

- Implemented fully automatic layout engine to generate parts of a magazine with sport-statistical data, which eliminated the need for a lengthy manual layout process
- Developed web based Interface for external customers to leverage in-house sports data
- Automate workflows in the production of a sports magazine
- <u>Leveraged knowledge</u> in Ruby, PHP, C/C++, Scheme, MSSQL, SXML, Quark

Software Developer

Lapp & Krentzlin

2003 - 2005

- Developed Borland C++ component to provide access to traffic sign database
- Implemented sophisticated reports for Lexware
- Leveraged knowledge in C++, Shell, MSSQL

EDUCATION

Fernuniversität Hagen

Computer Science

2003 - 2006

SKILLS

- Self driven learning
- Good communication skills
- Very good knowledge of programming languages, software design, software architecture and software development
- Very good understanding of functional programming and idiomatic use of functional abstractions
- Proficient with GraphQL, Scala, Scala, Ruby, Haskell, Scheme, MySQL, Git, Unix, AMQP
- Familiar with Go lang, Elixir, Rust, Clojure, Common Lisp, C/C++, PostgreSQL, Kubernetes, Redis, Memcached, Varnish

HOBBIES AND INTERESTS

- Programming language theory
- Distributed systems
- Music / Guitar
- Mindfulness